Anish K. Simhal

Durham, NC **☎** 571.721.9244 ⋈ aksimhal@gmail.com '• github.com/aksimhal

I completed my graduate studies at Duke University, studying image processing under the supervision of Dr. Guillermo Sapiro. My current research focuses on studying the effects of cord blood infusions on neurological development for children with autism spectrum disorder by analyzing their connectome. I also research methods for analyzing brain tissue labeled with antibodies and imaged via confocal microscopy.

Education

2014 – 2019 PhD — Electrical Engineering.
Duke University, Durham, NC.
Pratt School of Engineering — Dept. of Electrical Engineering

2014 – 2016 Masters of Science — Electrical Engineering.
Duke University, Durham, NC.
Pratt School of Engineering — Dept. of Electrical Engineering

2010 – 2014 Bachelor of Science — Electrical Engineering. University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA. School of Engineering and Applied Sciences

Computational Tools

Proficient Python, MATLAB, Git, Latex

Semi- 3D Design, 3D Printing, C++, C#, JAVA, LabVIEW, Android app development Proficient

Publications

- 2019 A. K. Simhal, K. L. H. Carpenter, S. Nadeem, J. Kurtzberg, A. Song, A. Tannenbaum, G. Sapiro, G. Dawson. "Graph curvature as a proxy for discerning robustness in brain networks for autism spectrum disorder." 2019. *In preparation*.
- 2019 A. K. Simhal, Y. Zuo, M. M. Perez, D. V. Madison, G. Sapiro, and K. D. Micheva. "Multifaceted changes in synaptic composition and astrocytic involvement in a mouse model of fragile x syndrome." 2019. *bioRxiv*.
- 2018 A. K. Simhal, B. Gong, J. S. Trimmer, R. J. Weinberg, S. J. Smith, G. Sapiro, and K. D. Micheva. "A computational synaptic antibody characterization tool for array tomography." 12, 2018. *Frontiers in Neuroanatomy*.
- 2018 M. N. Asiedu, A. K. Simhal, U. Chaudhary, J. L. Mueller, C. T. Lam, J. W. Schmitt, G. Venegas, G. Sapiro, and N. Ramanujam. "Development of algorithms for automated detection of cervical pre-cancers with a low-cost, point-of-care, pocket colposcope." 2018. *IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering*.
- 2018 M. N. Asiedu, A. K. Simhal, C. T. Lam, J. Mueller, U. Chaudhary, J. W. Schmitt, G. Sapiro, and N. Ramanujam. "Image processing and machine learning techniques to automate diagnosis of lugol's iodine cervigrams for a low-cost point-of-care digital colposcope." 2018. Optics and Biophotonics in Low-Resource Settings IV. Volume 10485. International Society for Optics and Photonics.
- 2017 A. K. Simhal, C. Aguerrebere, F. Collman, J. T. Vogelstein, K. D. Micheva, R. J. Weinberg, S. J. Smith, and G. Sapiro. "**Probabilistic fluorescence-based synapse detection.**" 2017. *PLoS Computational Biology*.

2014 A.K. Simhal, V.-G. Kanumuru, A. Holmes, and E. Berger. "Exploring the use of student taught classes to introduce new technical topics to engineering undergraduates." 2014. Frontiers in Education Conference, IEEE, pages 1–8.

Selected Poster Presentations

- 2018 SfN 2018 Annual Meeting (Nov 2018) Poster. **"An array tomography exploration tool: Exploring synapses from FMR1 knockout mice."** Anish K. Simhal, Kristina D. Micheva, Yi Zuo, Richard J. Weinberg, Stephen J. Smith, Guillermo Sapiro
- 2017 SfN 2017 Annual Meeting (Nov 2017) Poster. **"Automated Antibody Characterization for Array Tomography."** Anish K. Simhal, Belvin Gong, James Trimmer, Richard J. Weinberg, Stephen J. Smith, Guillermo Sapiro, Kristina D. Micheva
- 2017 SfN 2017 Annual Meeting (Nov 2017) Poster. **"Comparing Mouse and Human Synapses with Automated Probabilistic Synapse Analysis."** Kristina D. Micheva, Anish K. Simhal, Jonathan T. Ting, Andrew L. Ko, William W. Seeley, Edward F. Chang, Alissa Nana Li, Ed Lein, Forrest Collman, Daniel V. Madison, Richard J. Weinberg, Stephen J. Smith, Guillermo Sapiro
- 2016 SfN 2016 Annual Meeting (Nov 2016) Poster. **"Probabilistic Synapse Detection in Array Tomography."** Anish K. Simhal, Cecilia Aguerrebere, Forrest Collman, Joshua T. Vogelstein, Kristina D. Micheva, Richard J. Weinberg, Stephen J. Smith, Guillermo Sapiro
- 2015 NIPS 2015 (Dec 2015) Poster. "Computational statistics for whole brain CLARITY analysis using the Open Connectome Project. Anish K. Simhal, Will Gray Roncal, Kunal A. Lillaney, Kwame Kutten, Michael I. Miller, Joshua T. Vogelstein, Randal Burns, Li Ye, Raju Tomer, Karl Deisseroth, Guillermo Sapiro
- 2015 SfN 2015 Annual Meeting (Oct 2015) Poster. **"Computational statistics for whole brain CLARITY analysis using the Open Connectome Project.** Anish K. Simhal, Will Gray Roncal, Kunal A. Lillaney, Kwame Kutten, Michael I. Miller, Joshua T. Vogelstein, Randal Burns, Li Ye, Raju Tomer, Karl Deisseroth, Guillermo Sapiro

Selected Talks

- 2018 Simhal, Anish K et al. "A Computational Synaptic Antibody Characterization Tool for Array Tomography." School of Electrical Engineering, Tel Aviv University. 15 October 2018. Tel Aviv, Israel.
- 2018 Simhal, Anish K et al. "A Computational Synaptic Antibody Characterization and Screening Framework for Array Tomography." Data Dialogue, IID, Duke University. 22 March 2018. Durham, North Carolina.
- 2017 Simhal, Anish K et al. "Probabilistic fluorescence-based synapse detection." Facultad de Ingeniería, Universidad de la República. 6 November 2017. Montevideo, Uruguay.
- 2017 Simhal, Anish K et al. "Automated Antibody Characterization and Screening for Array Tomography via Probabilistic Synapse Detection." Seminario Interdisciplinario Procesamiento y Análisis de Imágenes Biomédicas, Universidad de la República. 9 November 2017. Montevideo, Uruguay.

Teaching Experience

- Spring 2016, Image Processing (Duke ECE 590) Teaching Assistant
 - 2017 Supported students taking the course in-person at Duke and online via Coursera.
- Spring 2014 **Digital Signal Processing (UVa ECE 4750/6750)** Teaching Assistant
 - Explained a variety of topics in DSP to both undergraduate and graduate students.
 - Created and graded weekly homework assignments and exams.
 - Held regular office hours attended by an average of 20+ students.
 - Fall 2012, Circuit Analysis (UVa ECE 2630) Teaching Assistant
 - 2013 Taught various circuit analysis techniques to second year EE/CPE students.
 - Demonstrated an array of lab skills, including using oscilloscopes.

- Fall 2011 Engineering Explorations 1st Year Seminar (UVa ENGR 1595) Instructor
 - Introduced and facilitated an "Explorations in Engineering" Seminar to provide 1st year students with an overview of all engineering disciplines – Coordinated with the Dean's Office to create and manage the curriculum.
- 2008-2015 Smithsonian National Air & Space Museum Education Volunteer
 - Dynamically adapted to a wide spectrum of age groups to educate and engage visitors from topics ranging from how an airplane flies to how astronauts live and work in space.

Leadership Experience

2018-present Bull City Classrooms — Founder.

- Created a nonprofit group address the needs of Durham Public Elementary School teachers.
- Engaged 400+ volunteers at 15+ events at local elementary schools
- Raised \$2,000+ from community partners to support these efforts
- www.bullcityclassrooms.org
- www.instagram.com/bullcityclassrooms
- 2016-2018 Little League Coach, Durham Boys and Girls Club Head Coach
 - Coached twelve children, ages 9-12, for the Durham Bulls Youth Athletic League organiza-
 - During the season, spent 10 hours a week with the children.
 - Organized practices, recruited assistant coaches, communicated with parents in English and Spanish.

Industry Experience

June/July Allen Institute for Brain Sciences, Synapse Biology — Summer Visitor

2016 - Worked with the synapse biology team, led by Dr. Stephen J. Smith, to develop new tools for detection synapses in array tomography data.

Summer Azure Summit Technology — Electrical Engineering Intern

- 2013 Developed a signal processing GUI in MATLAB to augment spectrogram analysis, digital down conversion, and other signal processing tools.
 - Designed various filters to equalize hardware system channel responses.

Summer Decisive Analytics Corporation — Image Processing Intern

- 2012 Transformed video footage from unmanned aerial vehicles to create panoramic imagery to augment existing map data.
 - Designed and executed object detection algorithms to track vehicles throughout a video using OpenCV libraries; wrote documentation.
 - Implemented and evaluated an image processing research paper in C++.

Summer EOIR Technologies, Inc. — Software Engineering Intern

- 2011 Developed video analysis software based on the Python and OpenCV libraries to analyze and augment the results of an object tracking algorithm.
 - Collaborated with engineers to develop and manage evolving requirements and specifications; learned the Software Development Life Cycle.

Awards

- 2019 Durham Public School Spark Advocate Award
 - Won in recognition of creating a nonprofit to engage the Durham community with Durham Public School teachers and staff.
- 2013 Microsoft Imagine Cup Entrepreneurship Competition 1st Place Innovation
 - Created a physical therapy application to provide patients performing exercises and stretches real-time feedback via the Kinect Sensor in C#.
 - Researched product development strategies, business models, and performed market analysis.

- 2013 Harrison Undergraduate Research Award
 - Won competitive Harrison Award for 'outstanding undergraduate research,' which provided substantial research funding. Presented by the Center for Undergraduate Excellence at U.Va.

Undergraduate Research Experience

- 2014 Heliotropism in Sunflowers @ VIVA Research Group Dr. Scott Acton, ECE
 - Researched and designed an algorithm to track the motion of sunflowers over extended periods of time. It is a fascinating problem due to the constantly evolving shape of the plant and the variety present within the species.
 - Collaborated and implemented the algorithm via MATLAB and delivered GUI to Dr. Blackman, U.Va Biology Dept.
- 2012-2014 Semi-Enclosed Area Occupancy Detection Dr. Archie Holmes, ECE
 - Designed an integrated wireless sensor platform to detect occupancy in semi-enclosed area, to help students find an empty study areas via a mobile application.
 - Constructed a full scale prototype by integrating a microprocessor, passive & thermal infrared sensors, and digital radios in a 3D printed custom enclosure.
- 2012-2013 INTERIA Wireless Health Research Dr. John Lach, ECE
 - Designed calibration procedure for an Ankle Foot Orthopedic device with multiple sensors and created software tool chain to support it.
 - Researched various activity classifications algorithms and created step counter.
 - Created program (BodySim) to scan in 3D models of the human body via the Microsoft Kinect in C++ to model human kinematics.

Selected News Articles

- 2019 9th Street Journal. "Bull City Classrooms ushers volunteers to Durham elementary schools." January 25th, 2019.
- 2014 UVA Today. "U.Va. Undergrads Track Foot Traffic to Make Study Areas More Accessible." March 18th, 2014.
- 2013 UVA Today. "From Programming Languages to Auto Mechanics, Engineering Students Give Teaching a Try." December 15th, 2013.
- 2013 UVA Today. "U.Va. Engineering Students Earn Microsoft's Imagine Cup for Innovation." June 28th, 2013.